<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<rfc category="bcp" submissionType="IETF" docName="draft-lemon-stub-networks-ps-01" ipr="trust200902"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3"
     scripts="Common,Latin" sortRefs="false"
     symRefs="true" tocDepth="3" tocInclude="true" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Stub Networks Problem Statement">Self-configuring Stub Networks: Problem Statement</title>
    <author initials="T" surname="Lemon" fullname="Ted Lemon">
      <organization>Apple, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>One Apple Park Way</street>
	  <city>Cupertino</city>
	  <region>California</region>
	  <country>United States of America</country>
	  <code>95014</code>
	</postal>
	<email>elemon@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2021" month="February" day="22"></date>
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>

	IETF currently provides protocols for automatically connecting single hosts to existing network infrastructure. This
	document describes a related problem: the problem of connecting a stub network (a collection of hosts behind a router)
	automatically to existing network infrastructure in the same manner.

      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section><name>Introduction</name>
      <t>

	This document describes the problem of linking stub networks to existing networks automatically, in the same way that hosts,
	when connected to an existing network, are able to discover network addressing parameters, information about routing, and
	services that are advertised on the network.

      </t>
      <t>
	There are several use cases for stub networks. Motivating factors include:
      </t>
      <ul>
	<li>

	    Transitory connectivity: a mobile device acting as a router for a set of co-located devices could connect to a network
	    and gain access to services for itself and for the co-located devices.  Such a stub network is unlikely to have more
	    than one stub router.

	  </li>
	  <li>

	    Incompatible media: for example, a constrained 802.15.4 network connected as a stub network to a WiFi or ethernet
	    infrastructure network.  In the case of an 802.15.4 network, it is quite possible that the devices used to link the
	    infrastructure network to the stub network will not be conceived of by the end user as routers.  Consequently, we cannot
	    assume that these devices will be on all the time. A solution for this use case will require some sort of commissioning
	    process for stub routers, and can't assume that any particular stub router will always be available; rather, any stub
	    router that is available must be able to adapt to current conditions to provide reachability.

	  </li>
	  <li>

	    Convenience: end users often connect devices to each other in order to extend networks

	  </li>
	</ul>
      <t>

	What makes stub networks a distinct type of network is simply that a stub network never provides transit between networks to
	which it is connected. The term "stub" refers to the way the network is seen by the link to which it is connected: there is
	reachability through a stub network router to the stub network from that link, but there is no reachability to any link
	beyond that one.

      </t>
      <t>

	Stub networks may be globally reachable, or may be only locally reachable. A host on a globally reachable stub network can
	interoperate with other hosts anywhere on the Internet. A host on a locally reachable stub network can only interoperate
	with hosts on the network link(s) to which it is connected.

      </t>
      <t>

	The goal of this document is to describe the minimal set of changes or behaviors required to use existing IETF
	specifications to support the stub network use case. The result should be a small set of protocol enhancements
	(ideally no changes at all to protocols) and should be deployable on existing networks without requiring changes
	to those networks.  Both the locally-reachable and globally-reachable use case should be able to be made to work,
	and ideally the globally-reachable use case should build on what is used to make the locally-reachable use case
	work, rather than requiring two separate solutions.

      </t>
      <section anchor="interop-goals"><name>Interoperability Goals</name>
	<t>
	  What we mean by "interoperate" is that a host on a stub network:
	</t>
	  <ul>
	    <li>is discoverable by applicable hosts that are not on the stub network</li>
	    <li>is able to acquire an IP address that can be used to communicate with applicable hosts not on the stub network</li>
	    <li>has reachability to the network(s) to which applicable hosts are attached</li>
	    <li>is reachable from the network(s) to which applicable hosts are attached</li>
	  </ul>
	<t>

	  Discoverability here means "discoverable using DNS, or DNS Service Discovery".  As an example, when one host connected to
	  a specific WiFi network wishes to discover services on hosts connected to that same WiFi network, it can do so using
	  multicast DNS (RFC6762), which is an example of DNS Service Discovery.  Similarly, when a host on some other network
	  wishes to discover the same service, it must use DNS-based DNS Service Discovery <xref target="RFC6763"/>.  In both cases,
	  "discoverable using DNS" means that the host has an entry in the DNS.

	</t>
	<t>

	  NOTE: it may be tempting to ask, why do we lump discoverability in with reachability and addressability, both of
	  which are essentially Layer 3 issues? The answer is that it does us no good to automatically set up connectivity
	  between stub network hosts and infrastructure hosts if the infrastructure hosts have no mechanism for learning
	  about the availability of services provided by stub network hosts. For stub networks that only consume cloud services
	  this will not be an issue, but for stub networks that provide services, e.g. the incompatible media use case
	  mentioned earlier, discoverability is necessary in order for stub network connectivity to be useful.

	</t>
	<t>

	  Ability to acquire an IP address that can be used to communicate means that the IP address a host on the stub network
	  acquires can be used to communicate with it by hosts on neighbor networks, for locally reachable stub networks, or by
	  hosts on any network, for globally reachable networks. Various means of providing such addresses are discussed later.

	</t>
	<t>

	  Reachability to networks on which applicable hosts are attached means that when a host on the stub network has the IP
	  address of an applicable host with which it intends to communicate, that host knows of a next-hop router to which it can
	  send datagrams, so that they will ultimately reach the host with that IP address.

	</t>
	<t>

	  Reachability from networks on which applicable hosts are attached means that when such a host has a datagram destined for
	  an IP address on the stub network, a next-hop router is known by that host which, when the datagram is sent to that
	  router, will ultimately result in the datagram reaching the intended stub network host.

	</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="usability-goals"><name>Usability Goals</name>
	<t>

	  In addition to the interoperability goals we've described above, the additional goal for stub networks is that they be
	  able to be connected automatically, with no user intervention.  The experience of connecting a stub network to an
	  infrastructure should be as straightforward as connecting a new host to the same infrastructure network.

	</t>
      </section>
      <section><name>State of the Art</name>
	<t>

	  Currently there is one known way to accomplish what we are describing here [[Michael, does ANIMA have a second way?]]. The
	  Homenet working group produced a protocol, HomeNet Configuration Protocol (HNCP), the purpose of which is to allow a
	  collection of routers to self-configure. HNCP is not technically constrained to home environments; in principle, it can
	  work in any environment.

	</t>
	<t>

	  The problem with HNCP is twofold.  First, it only works if it is deployed on all routers within the network infrastructure
	  for a site. Secondly, it attempts to do too much, and invents too much that is new.  Let's look at these in order.

	</t>
	<t>

	  First, HNCP only works when deployed on all routers within the network infrastructure. To be clear, this does not mean
	  that it is impossible to use HNCP on a network where, for instance, the edge router(s) do not support HNCP. What it does
	  mean is that if this configuration works, the reason it works is that the network supports prefix delegation to routers
	  inside the network. So a router doing HNCP can get a prefix using prefix delegation from, for example, an edge router, and
	  this will work.

	</t>
	<t>

	  Unfortunately, the way that such an HNCP server should behave is not documented, and it's not actually clear how it should
	  behave. What if the DHCP server allocates it a /64?  HNCP is designed to get a larger prefix and subdivide it&mdash;there
	  is no provision for requesting multiple delegations. So if we wanted to use HNCP to solve this problem, we would need to
	  do additional work.

	</t>
	<t>

	  Secondly, HNCP tries to do too much, and invents too much that is new. HNCP is a complicated protocol for propagating
	  network configuration information in a mesh. It does not assume that any network is a stub network, and because of that,
	  using it to support stub networks is needlessly complicated.

	</t>
	<t>

	  Despite having been an IETF proposed standard since 2016, and having been worked on for quite some time before that, it is
	  not possible to purchase a router that implements HNCP.  There exists a prototype implementation in OpenWRT, but getting
	  it to actually work is problematic, and many problems have been left unsolved, and would be quite difficult to solve with
	  additional standards work.

	</t>
	<t>

	  We know this because several participants in the Homenet Working Group have tried to implement make it work, and yet as
	  yet we have made no documentable progress, and indeed the Homenet Working Group appears to be on the verge of closing.

	</t>
	<t>

	  Because of the first point&mdash;the utter lack of commercial implementations of HNCP&mdash;any stub network solution that
	  is intended to be deployed to arbitrary networks can't rely on the availability of HNCP. This may come in the future, but
	  is not available now, and may never be.  Therefore, whatever approach is taken MAY use HNCP if available, but MUST work
	  without HNCP. Therefore, using HNCP represents additional implementation complexity; whether this is worth doing is
	  something that should be considered, but because using HNCP is necessarily optional, it probably makes the most sense to
	  assume that any functionality provided by HNCP will be external to the stub network router, and that the stub network
	  router itself need not participate in the HNCP mesh.

	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section><name>Possible Approaches</name>
      <section><name>Proxy ND</name>
	<section><name>Reachability</name>
	  <t>

	    Proxy Neighbor Discovery provides reachability to hosts on the stub network by simply pretending that they are on the
	    infrastructure network. This reachability can be local or global depending on what IPv6 service (if any) is available on
	    the infrastructure link.  The use of Proxy ND for providing connectivity to stub networks is described in
	    <xref target="I-D.ietf-6lo-backbone-router"/>.

	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Addressability</name>
	  <t>

	    If IPv6 service is available on the infrastructure link, this service can be used to provide addressability on
	    the stub network, and also provides addressability on the infrastructure link.

	  </t>
	  <t>

	    If IPv6 service is not available on the infrastructure link, addressability for proxy ND can be provided by
	    advertising an on-link autoconfigurable prefix in a Router Advertisement offered by the stub router.

	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Discoverability</name>
	  <t>

	    Discoverability for stub network hosts can be provided using DNS-SD service registration protocol on the stub
	    network, in combination with an Advertising Proxy on the stub router which would advertise registered services
	    to the infrastructure link.

	  </t>
	  <t>

	    Discoverability of infrastructure link hosts by stub network hosts can be provided using a DNS-SD discovery proxy and/or
	    regular DNS. As long as the stub network requires that each stub router provide a DNS-SD Discovery Proxy and
	    also provide name resolution, this will work even in the multiple stub router case.

	  </t>

	</section>
	<section><name>Requirements</name>
	    <ul>
	      <li>

		The infrastructure must either provide IPv6 service, or not block the provision of IPv6 service by the stub router.

	      </li>
	      <li>

		Hosts on the infrastructure link must support IPv6 and must support IPv6 neighbor discovery.

	      </li>
	      <li>

		Every stub host must register with at least one stub router that will do proxy ND for it.

	      </li>

	      <li>

		Routers must share proxy ND information, or else each router is a single point of failure for the set of hosts that
		have registered with it.

	      </li>

	      <li>

		Sharing proxy ND information requires new protocol work

	      </li>
	    </ul>
	</section>
	<section><name>Observations</name>
	  <t>

	    Can definitely work in specific circumstances, but probably doesn't lend itself to full automation.

	  </t>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section><name>Stub reachability using RA</name>
	<section><name>Reachability</name>
	  <t>

	    Reachability to the stub network is provided using the Route Information Option <xref target="RFC4191"/> in a router
	    advertisement <xref target="RFC4861"/> issued by the stub router. Since the stub router does not provide IPv6
	    connectivity, it must not advertise itself as a default router.  Each stub router can provide a default route to the
	    stub network.

	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Addressability</name>
	  <t>

	    Addressability on the stub network is provided using a ULA prefix generated by the stub router. Addressibility on the
	    infrastructure link is either provided by the infrastructure, or else must be provided by the stub router.

	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Discoverability</name>

	  <t>

	    Discoverability for this approach is the same as for the Proxy ND approach.

	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Requirements</name>
	    <ul>
	      <li>

		Infrastructure network must not block router advertisements.

	      </li>
	      <li>

		Hosts on the infrastructure network must support IPv6, must support the use of non-default routes as described in
		<xref target="RFC4191" />, and must support routing through non-default routers (routers with a router lifetime of
		0).

	      </li>
	      <li>

		Stub routers must cooperate with other stub routers in announcing an on-link prefix to the stub network.

	      </li>
	      <li>

		Stub routers must cooperate with infrastructure routers in announcing an on-link prefix for the infrastructure
		network. Stub routers must not advertise an on-link prefix when an on-link prefix is already present.

	      </li>
	    </ul>
	</section>
	<section><name>Observations</name>
	  <t>
	    This option has the advantage of relying primarily on ordinary IPv6 routing, as opposed to workarounds like
	    proxy neighbor discovery or NAT64.  The cooperation that is required between stub routers is minimal: they
	    need simply minimize the advertising of redundant information. When redundant information is advertised,
	    this is an aesthetic issue rather than an operational issue, and can be allowed to heal gradually.
	  </t>
	  <t>

	    Additionally, this option does not require any new behavior on the part of existing hosts or routers. It does assume
	    that infrastructure hosts actually implement <xref target="RFC4191"/>, but it is not unreasonable to expect that this
	    either is already the case, or can easily be accomplished. It also assumes that the infrastructure does not
	    enforce <xref target="RFC6105">RA Guard</xref>. This is compatible with the recommendations in RFC6105, which
	    indicates that RA guard needs to be configured before it is enabled.

	  </t>

	  <t>
	    The approach described in this section only makes it possible for stub network hosts to interoperate with
	    hosts on the link to which the stub router is directly attached. The "Global Reachability" approach talks
	    about how to establish interoperability between stub network hosts and hosts on links to which the stub
	    network is not directly attached.
	  </t>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section><name>Global reachability</name>
	<t>

	  Global reachability for stub networks requires either the use of NAT64, or else the presence of global
	  IPv6 service on the link.  As such it is more of an add-on approach than a different approach.  This section
	  talks about a specific example of global reachability: how to make global reachability work for the
	  "Stub Reachability using RA" approach mentioned earlier.

	</t>
	<t>

	  The "global reachability" approach has applicability both in the literal sense, and also in the sense of
	  "reachability beyond the link to which the stub router is directly attached."  The behavior of the stub
	  router is the same in both cases: it is up to the network infrastructure what prefix is delegated to the
	  stub router, and what reachability is provided.

	</t>
	<section><name>Reachability</name>
	  <t>

	    Reachability in this case requires integration into the routing infrastructure. This is most easily accomplished
	    by having the DHCPv6 prefix delegation server add an entry in the routing table pointing to the stub router
	    to which the prefix has been delegated. Stub routers can also advertise reachability to the stub network using
	    router advertisements, but these will only work on the local link.

	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Addressability</name>
	  <t>

	    Addressability in this case for hosts on the infrastructure link is assumed to be provided by the infrastructure,
	    since we are relying on the infrastructure to provide DHCPv6 prefix delegation.  Addressibility on the stub
	    network is provided using the prefix acquired with prefix delegation.

	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Discoverability</name>
	  <t>
	    Discoverability for devices on the link to which the stub network is attached can be done as described earlier under
	    the "Proxy ND" approach.
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Requirements</name>
	  <ul>
	      <li>

		Infrastructure network must support prefix allocation using DHCPv6 prefix delegation.

	      </li>
	      <li>

		Infrastructure network must install routes to prefixes provided using DHCPv6 prefix delegation.

	      </li>
	      <li>

		In the case of multiple stub routers, stub routers must cooperate both in acquiring and renewing prefixes
		acquired using prefix delegation. Stub routers must communicate complete routing information to the DHCPv6
		prefix delegation server so that it can install routes.

	      </li>
	    </ul>
	</section>
	<section><name>Observations</name>
	  <t>

	    This approach should be a proper superset of the "Stub Reachability using RA" approach. The primary technical
	    challenge here is specifying how multiple stub routers cooperate in doing prefix delegation.

	  </t>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section><name>Support for IPv4</name>
	<t>

	  This document generally assumes that stub networks only support IPv6. Bidirectional reachability for IPv4 can be provided
	  using a combination of NAT44 and <xref target="RFC6887">Port Control Protocol</xref>. The use of NAT44 and PCP in this way
	  has already been solved and need not be discussed here.

	</t>
	<section><name>Reachability</name>
	  <t>

	    Reachability is complicated for NAT64.  Typical NAT64 deployments provide reachability from the stub network to
	    the rest of the Internet, but do not provide reachability from the rest of the internet to the stub network.
	    As with NAT44 and PCP, this type of reachability is a solved problem and need not be discussed here.  To provide
	    complete reachability to the IPv4 internet, a stub router must not only provide reachability to the cloud, but also
	    reachability from the cloud. That additional work is discussed here.

	  </t>
	  <t>

	    To provide reachability from the cloud to devices on the network, devices on the network will need to obtain
	    static mappings from the external IPv4 address and a port to the internal IPv6 address and a port.  There are
	    three ways to do this:
	  </t>
	    <ul>
	      <li>The stub host can use Port Control Protocol to register a port, and then advertise that using SRP.</li>
	      <li>The stub host can simply register using SRP, and then SRP can establish a port mapping.</li>
	    </ul>

	  <t>

	    The first option has the advantage that the stub host is in complete control over what is advertised.
	    However, it places an additional burden on the stub host which may not be desirable: the host has to
	    implement PCP and link the PCP port allocation to the SRP registration.

	  </t>
	  <t>

	    For a constrained network device, it is most likely preferable to combine the two transactions: the SRP server can
	    receive the registration from the stub host and acquire a PCP mapping for it, and then register an AAAA and A record for
	    the host along with an SRV record for the IPv4 and IPv6 mappings. The hostname mapping would need to be different for
	    the A record and the AAAA record in order to avoid spurious connections to the IPv4 port on the IPv6 address and vice
	    versa.

	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Addressability</name>
	  <t>

	    Addressability on the stub network can be provided using a ULA prefix specific to the stub network or, if NAT64 is
	    being used in addition to one of the other solutions discussed here, the prefix allocated on the stub network
	    for that purpose can also be used for NAT64.

	  </t>
	  <t>

	    IPv4 addressability on the infrastructure network is provided by the infrastructure network.  It is also possible
	    that the infrastructure network is an IPv6 network. In that case, the NAT64 edge router may be provided by the
	    infrastructure as well.

	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Discoverability</name>
	  <t>
	    The discoverability described for the "ND Proxy" approach should work here as well, except for the
	    caveat mentioned above under "reachability".
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section><name>Requirements</name>
	  <ul>
	      <li>
		TBD
	      </li>
	    </ul>
	</section>
	<section><name>Observations</name>
	  <t>

	    Support for NAT64 may be required for some deployments. NAT64 support requires either close cooperation between stub
	    routers, or else requires that the NAT64 translation be done externally.  The latter choice is likely quite a bit
	    easier; solutions that provide load balancing and high availability are already available on the market, and hence do
	    not require that the stub routers perform this function. This is expected to be the best approach to serve the needs
	    of consumers of this capability.

	  </t>
	</section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section><name>Discoverability Options</name>
      <t>

	We can divide the set of hosts needing to be discovered and the set of hosts needing to discover them into
	four categories:
      </t>
	<ul>
	  <li>Stub network hosts (stub hosts)</li>
	  <li>Hosts that are on the link to which the stub network is directly connected (direct hosts)</li>
	  <li>Hosts that are on other links within the same infrastructure (infrastructure hosts)</li>
	  <li>Hosts that are on other links not within the same infrastructure (cloud hosts)</li>
	</ul>
      <t>

	To enable stub hosts to discover direct hosts, a <xref target="RFC8766">Discovery Proxy</xref> can be used.
	This must be resident on any stub network router that is seen by the stub host as a resolver.

      </t>
      <t>

	To enable stub hosts to discover infrastructure hosts using DNS-SD <xref target="RFC6763"/>, the infrastructure
	must provide support for RFC6763 service discover using DNS.

      </t>
      <t>

	To enable stub hosts to discover infrastructure hosts and cloud hosts using DNS, DNS resolution must be provided by the stub
	router, and the infrastructure must additionally provide the stub router with the ability to resolve names.

      </t>

      <t>

	To enable direct hosts to discover stub hosts, stub routers must implement a DNS-SD Advertising Proxy. Stub hosts must
	register with the advertising proxy using SRP.

      </t>
      <t>

	To enable infrastructure hosts to discover stub hosts, stub routers must provide authoritative DNS service for the
	stub network link so that it can be integrated into the infrastructure DNS-SD service. To do this automatically will
	require additional protocol work.

      </t>
      <t>

	To enable cloud hosts to discover stub hosts, stub hosts would need to register with the DNS, and the infrastructure
	would need to make those registrations available globally, perhaps with whitelisting.  This is probably not a very
	widely applicable use case, and we do not consider specifying how this works to be part of the work of this document.

      </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>Multiple Egress, Multiple Link</name>
      <t>

	In the case of a stub network that has multiple stub routers, it is possible that, either when the stub network is initially
	set up, or subsequently, one or more stub routers might be connected to a different infrastructure link than one or more
	other stub routers.  There are two viable approaches to this problem:

      </t>
	<ul>
	  <li>declare it out of scope and have the stub routers prevent such configurations</li>
	  <li>make sure that stub routers attached to each infrastructure link provide complete service on that link</li>
	</ul>

      <t>
	Explain further.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="mgt"><name>Management Considerations</name>
      <t>
	TBD
      </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Privacy Considerations</name>

      <t>

	In the locally reachable case, privacy is protected in the sense that names published locally are only visible to devices
	connected locally.  This may be insufficient privacy in some cases.

      </t>
      <t>

	In the globally reachable case, discoverability has privacy implications. Unfiltered automatic discoverability is probably
	not a good idea in the globally reachable case.  If automatic discoverability is provided, some filtering mechanism would
	need to be specified.

      </t>

    </section>

    <section><name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>

	TBD

      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA"><name>IANA considerations</name>
      <t>No new actions are required by IANA for this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4191.xml" />
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml" />
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6105.xml" />
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6763.xml" />
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6887.xml" />
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8766.xml" />
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6lo-backbone-router.xml" />
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
     Local variables:
     mode: sgml
     fill-column:132
     sgml-omittag:t
     sgml-shorttag:t
     sgml-namecase-general:t
     sgml-general-insert-case:lower
     sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
     sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
     sgml-indent-step:2
     sgml-indent-data:t
     sgml-parent-document:nil
     sgml-exposed-tags:nil
     sgml-local-catalogs:nil
     sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
     End:
  -->
